RAKESH KUMAR RAI

Technical Assistant

• Delhi, India • +91-9870443528 • rakeshrai71@gmail.com • linkedin.com/in/rakesh-kumar-rai

Expert with 9 years of experience in Web Development and More than 4 years of experience in IT Networks and Data Centers, Now, I am ready to work in an innovative and competitive world where I can utilize my entire logic and efforts in the growing IT industry.

SKILLS

Web Development and Digital Marketing:

HTML, HTML5, CSS, SASS, PHP, MySQL, XHTML, Bootstrap, JavaScript, JSON, Ajax, jQuery, WordPress, Drupal, SeedProd, Photoshop, CorelDraw, Web Hosting Management, REST API, OSCommerce, Apache, Nginx, Microsoft IIS, XAMPP, WAMP, LAMP, Brand Awareness, Lead Generation, Marketing Campaigns, Online Marketing, E-mail Marketing, Social Media Marketing, Google Analytics, PPC, Google AdWords, Google Workspace, Google Search Console.

Network Engineering and Cyber Security:

Cisco Switching, Fortinet Firewall, VLAN, CDP, Networking Protocols, VOIP, TCP/IP & OSI Model, Cisco UCS M4 Server, Wireshark, HP Blade System c7000, Tyrone SAS-SAN, Troubleshooting, DHCP, DNS, IPV4, ARP, WebSocket, Backup Management, Group Policy, Cloud Backup, OpenStack, VMware, Hyper-V, Web Security, IT Security, Vulnerability Assessment, Burp Suite, OWASP, Trend Micro Server.

Software Development:

C, Core Java, C# (Preliminary).

PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

National Institute of Technology, Delhi, India

06/2017 - Present

Technical Assistant

- Maintaining and administering computer networks and related computing environments including systems software, applications software, hardware, and configurations.
- Monitoring network performance to determine if adjustments need to be made.
- Protecting data, software, and hardware by coordinating, planning, and implementing network security measures.
- Installing, configuring, and supporting network equipment including routers, proxy servers, Web Servers, switches, WAN accelerators, DNS, and DHCP.
- Configuring firewalls, routing, and switching to maximize network efficiency and security.
- Designing, configuring, and testing networking software, computer hardware, and operating system software.
- Providing technical support on-site or via remote-access systems.
- Repairing hardware malfunctions, software issues, and networking problems.
- Implementation and Configurations in NVR & IP CCTV.
- Installing and maintaining desktop PCs, printers, OS, and applications.

- Antivirus installation on all desktops and laptops.
- Fault-finding in laptops and desktops.
- Provide assistance and support to colleagues in IT-related matters.

CT Group of Institutions, Jalandhar, India

07/2013 - 06/2017

Web Developer

- Developing and maintaining the front-end functionality of websites.
- Designing and building web pages based on suggested layouts, writing cross-browser compliant XHTML, CSS & JavaScript.
- Troubleshooting problems with performance or user experience.
- Identifying problems uncovered by customer feedback and testing and correcting or referring problems to appropriate personnel for correction.
- Integrating analytics tools, Chatbots, Heatmap, and others tracking user data.
- Providing tailored data sets for the executives on a weekly basis.
- Performing research on current benchmark trends and audience preferences.
- Designing and implementing social media strategy to align with business goals.
- Facilitating brand scaling and company awareness through various social media channels
- Monitoring campaigns and analyzing obtained data.
- Ensuring progress on all platforms by using analytical tools such as Google Analytics and others.
- Integrate data from various back-end services and databases.
- Creating and maintaining software documentation.
- Maintaining and updating websites.
- Resolving web bugs and running usability tests.

CERTIFICATIONS

 Certified in ET80- Sophos Firewall v19.0 Engineer from Sophos. 	08/2022
 Certified in WordPress from Udemy, Inc. 	08/2018
 Certified in Digital Marketing from Udemy, Inc. 	08/2018
 Certified in IBM Rational Software from IBM India. 	12/2013
 Certified in C language from CMC Ltd., India. 	11/2011

EDUCATION

IK Gujral Punjab Technical University, Jalandhar, India Master of Technology (Part-Time)

07/2014-07/2017

• Computer Science and Engineering

IK Gujral Punjab Technical University, Jalandhar, India Bachelor of Technology

07/2009-07/2013

Information Technology

TRAINING AND INTERNSHIPS

- Sophos Firewall training on July 30, 2022, from Mikroz InfoSecurity Pvt. Ltd., Delhi, India.
- Cyber Security online course on June 16, 2021, from Udemy Inc.
- Digital Marketing online course on August 31, 2018, from Udemy Inc.
- Cisco CCNA online course on August 31, 2018, from Udemy Inc.
- WordPress online course on August 31, 2018, from Udemy Inc.
- IBM Rational Certified training, December 2013 from IBM, India.
- Six months of industrial training, December 2012 to May 2013 from Naresh i Technologies, Hyderabad, India.
- Six weeks of summer training, 16th June to 27th July 2011 from CETPA Infotech Pvt. Ltd., Lucknow, India.
- Core Java Certification training, February to April 2011 from PurpleLeap, Bangalore, India.
- C Language training, 10th October to 17th November 2011 from CMC Ltd., Lucknow, India.

AWARDS

 Received Award from Sh. Arpit Shukla, IPS, and Commissioner of Police Jalandhar and Election Commission of India for 72 Hours Mobile App during Punjab Elections in 2017 (Technologies applied: jQuery, PHP, MySQL).

LANGUAGES

- English C1 Level
- Hindi (native)

HOBBIES

- Internet Surfing
- Play Football
- Play Guitar

PERSONAL PROFILE

• Date of Birth: 24-04-1992

• Gender: Male

Nationality: IndiansMarital Status: Single

I hereby declare that all the information given above is true to the best of my knowledge.

Date: 08/01/2023 Place: Delhi, India

Rakesh Kumar Rai